Binary search is something that you
might have learned in your initial
programming days. But you might be
surprised to know that it involves some
of the most efficient algorithms and it
is also used in a lot of production
workloads almost every day. So in this
particular video we are going to explore
more about this pattern. Hello friends,
welcome back to my channel.
When you think about binary search, what
is the first thing that comes to your
mind? It is not simply looking through a
sorted array and finding an element. It
has some of the most practical use
cases. For example, when I take a book,
let us say I have to search for the page
number 78. My general idea to find that
page will be I will look at the middle
page approximately middle and then look
at where I landed. I landed on 156. So I
know for sure that the page 78 that I'm
trying to search will be in the first
half. I can immediately discard the
remaining half of the search space. So
what is this doing? At every iteration
you reduce your first space by half and
it may feel that it is very small but
when you do it for a very large data set
the order of log and time complexity
actually becomes very very fast and that
is why this divide and conquer technique
can help you to solve a lot of problems.
So let us start off with something very
very basic. How do you actually apply
the binary search? So let us say I am
given a sorted array and you have to
search for a number. You can see that I
have this sorted array with me. It is
sorted in an ascending order and I have
to search for the number three. A linear
search would mean that you start from
the beginning and then keep on
traversing the array until unless you
find your number. But with a binary
search, you can take advantage of the
fact that your array is already sorted.
The basic idea for a binary search is
that I will have a left pointer and I
will have a right pointer. Now based
upon these two indexes, I can look at my
middle element. I land at my middle
element and that is four. Now how am I
taking advantage of this? I have to
search for the element three. It is very
sure that all of the elements after this
particular element will be greater. So
what does that mean? my result it won't
exist over here. I can straight away
discard this particular array but I am
now left with an even smaller array. So
what do I do next? I will update my
right pointer and I am going to move it
at this particular location. Once again
you take the left and right find out the
middle element and then again compare it
with the number you have to search. This
time your number is higher. So what had
we done in the first iteration? In the
first iteration, we got rid of some part
of the array. In the second iteration, I
can get rid of some more additional
array. So now what will happen is my
sample space gets even more smaller. You
see how in just two iterations, I am now
looking at such a small space. That is
the power of binary search. And that is
how you can quickly look up elements in
a sorted array. So that is the very
basic idea upon which this pattern is
built. We are looking at sorted numbers,
sorted sequences and then we divide and
conquer until we get the solution.
Similarly, you can now extend this
pattern. For example, take a look at
this particular question. Search insert
position. What you have to do is you are
given a certain array and you have to
tell me where can I insert the number 15
such that this array remains sorted. How
would you approach it with a linear
method? you will start to navigate your
entire array and you will keep on going
ahead until you reach a number that is
bigger than 15. It simply means that you
will have to insert 15 at this
particular position. So you return this
position as your answer. This is the
method, right? How can binary search
help you? Once again, what I'm going to
do is I will take up two pointers left
and right. What is the middle element?
The middle element is four. So in just
one instant I know that this number that
I'm inserting it will never be inserted
at the left of this middle element. So I
can straight away discard this entire
space. Right? I am only left with this
smaller space now. So what I will do is
I will update my left pointer over here.
What do you do in the next iteration?
Again you will apply the binary search
and you will land at a middle element.
So what do we know now? We know that I
will not find my result even here. So
what am I doing over here? At each step
I'm reducing my sample space. And now I
can simply say that okay after this
particular position I will want to
insert my element because I have removed
this half of the array also. My pointers
have now moved. Look at left and right.
Right is at 11 and I know that all of
these elements are greater than 15. So
where will it go? It will definitely go
between 11 and the remaining elements.
So that is your answer. Once again,
binary search help you to quickly get to
the solution. You might have noticed
that in both these examples, my array
was sorted in an ascending order from
beginning all the way towards the end.
There are also different questions
possible where an array might be sorted
but it is rotated also. What does that
mean? For example, I have this
particular problem. You have to search
for a number in a rotated sorted array.
So look at this particular array. It is
sorted but rotated also. Because if you
start from minus12, all of these numbers
are in an ascending order. And now it is
rotated to find other numbers in an
ascending order also 11 and 20. So the
array is sorted. Can you leverage the
binary search? Yes, but you might want
to have some additional checks also. For
example, if you try to apply binary
search in the most conventional way, you
have a left pointer and a right pointer.
What will happen? You get the middle
element. Let us say you will have your
mid somewhere over here. Correct? Now,
as soon as you find the mid, notice what
will happen. one half of the array will
always be sorted and the other half of
the array will again be a rotated sorted
array. And how can you check that? Just
look at the first element and the last
element. If the first element is smaller
than the last element, it means that
this array is completely sorted.
However, if the first element is larger
than the last element, it means that
this array is again a rotated sorted
array. So you can find a problem within
a sub problem. Right? If you also look
back at the original problem, the first
element is greater than the last
element. That is why this array was
rotated and sorted. So what does this
land up to? I can say that I will need
to find my number within this particular
array because I have to look for three
and three will lie somewhere between 1
and 8. So what can I do immediately? I
can discard this particular array and I
can safely apply my binary search
technique as usual in this part of the
array. That's it. Binary search can help
me again. But what happened if I would
be looking for a number let us say 20
over here. I have determined that okay
this part of the array is sorted. But
will you be able to find a 20 in here?
No. Because the largest number is 8
itself. So what will happen now? You are
going to remove this entire search space
and you are left with this particular
array. You will again take your left
pointer and the right pointer. And now
once again you will try to partition
your array. As soon as you partition it,
once again you will be left with one
half of the array that is sorted and one
half of the array that might be rotated
and sorted. So once again it is a
repeated pattern and you can use the
same technique to search for this number
in the remaining halves as well. So once
again applying binary search two times
helped you just with a little bit of
slight logic. Now when you think about
it there is a lot of things that go
behind a binary search framework. The
binary search algorithm is just kind of
a tip of the iceberg. You are all
knowing the common algorithm. Take a
left pointer. Take a right pointer
divide by two get the mid position and
then proceed ahead. That is just the
algorithm. But underneath a lot of other
things are happening at each instance.
You just half the search space that will
greatly help you with your very huge
data sets and that is why you have
logarithmic time complexity. That is the
best time complexity you can practically
have. Along with it, you also have
adaptive problem solving because based
upon certain conditions, you can still
apply the binary search technique and we
are going to see more of this in the
upcoming problems that I have to discuss
with you. The last part is really very
very interesting. Searching for answers.
This is the time when we apply binary
search in answers itself. But let us
wait before getting to it. The next type
of problem that I want to discuss is
finding the first and the last position
in a certain array over here. If you
notice I have this sorted array
available and it straight away means you
can try to apply the binary search
algorithm. You see that all of this
array is sorted but this number three is
repeated several times. And what do you
have to do for this given particular
number? You need to tell me the first
position and the last position. So when
you're actually searching, are you
searching for the number three? No, you
are searching for the first position of
number three. Just look at all of these
threes. They may look the same, but this
first three is very different from all
of these threes. And this last three is
again very different. How? For the first
three, the left element is smaller and
the right element is equal to three. And
for the last three, the left element is
equal and the right element is greater.
So technically we need to apply the
binary search algorithm two times. For
the first time we will try to find a
three which has the left element smaller
and the right element as equal. And then
we will again apply the binary search
technique to find where the left element
is equal and the right element is
greater. So let us say you want to find
the leftmost occurrence first. You are
going to apply your binary search
technique. You take up two pointers and
then you land at the middle element. You
see that okay this is a three. But is
this the three you want? No. You want a
three where the left element is smaller
but the right element is equal. This is
not your scenario but it is a three. So
you know that I will find my leftmost
element somewhere over here. So what can
I do? I can simply get rid of this half
of the array. I reduced my search space.
And now what will I do? I will take up
my right pointer and I'm going to move
it over here. Once again apply the
binary search technique and you will
land here. Ultimately what is going to
happen is you will land at this
particular three where your condition is
satisfied. You found out the leftmost
position. Similarly, you will apply the
same technique to find out the rightmost
position and you are going to land at
this particular three. So once again
applying a binary search by adapting you
adapted to a certain condition and then
you found out your answer. Similarly
there is one more problem statement also
finding the peak index in a mountain
array. Now a mountain array is just a
madeup word. Just look at this
particular array. If you notice, this
array has elements that keep on
increasing all the way up to 8 and then
they start to decrease again. So
technically, what are you looking over
here? You have to find a peak in a
mountain array. And this is a mountain
because it increases and then decreases.
Where is the peak? The peak is this
particular element. You have to return
this location. But you are not searching
for eight. Neither you are searching for
any specific element. What are you
searching for? You are searching for an
element which is greater than the left
element and which is greater than the
right element. And this is true only for
the peak element. If you notice for all
the other elements, this is the
scenario. You will only have one element
which is greater than its left and right
as well. So how do you adapt for binary
search? Once again you will take two
pointers and now are you looking for
something? Yes, but it is not the
element. You will sort and you will try
to look at the middle position. You
found out this middle position but over
here this particular number is not the
peak because the left number and the
right number they they are smaller and
larger respectively. So you know that
hey my peak does not exist over here. So
either your peak is going to exist in
this part or your peak is going to exist
in this part. You can apply the same
technique recursively on both these
parts and ultimately you will find a
specific number which is greater than
both the left element and the right
element. Once again binary search help
you to narrow down the entire space and
you adapted your binary search algorithm
according to the condition that you have
to solve for. From all these examples,
what do you understand about binary
search? It is not just looking at a
sorted array. Binary search is an
algorithm or a pattern which you can
adapt and solve and apply at multiple
different places. And we are certainly
going to see more examples on it. But
you might be getting a general idea. For
example, if you have a monotonic search
space, that means you know a certain
pattern. You know things are going to
increase and things are going to
decrease. So there is a certain pattern
you can follow that is a straightaway
giveaway that you can apply the binary
search technique over here. Similarly
try to think how we were adapting to the
situation. It was not just that we
looked at a specific number. You are
actually trying to determine a boolean
condition based upon a certain condition
if it is true or false. You can decide
to reject one half of the array and then
only search in a defined space. And that
gives me the next point. Your search
space is defined. If you are not sure
where the answer can be, then binary
search will never help you. Binary
search is always good for spaces which
are monotonic in nature and you know the
limits as well because only then you
will be able to have a left pointer and
a right pointer, right? and then you can
narrow down and this brings me to a very
interesting concept. You do not have to
apply the binary search just on the
given input set. I know that this is the
first thought that comes to our mind. As
soon as we see a problem, we try to
analyze the input and we will try to
apply the binary search technique on it.
And sometimes we may realize, hey, I
can't even apply binary search over
here. But that is not always true.
Sometimes you can also apply the binary
search on your answer space as well. And
that is why I mentioned your search
space should be defined. You must know
that okay I can have my maximum answers
between zero and this particular limit.
So let us take up an example on this
particular scenario. There is a
particular question on lead code
capacity to ship packages within D days.
The idea over here is very very simple.
You have packages that arrive in this
following order and these are the
weights of these packages. So first
package is 3 kg then 2 kg then 2 kg 4 1
and then again 4 kg. What you have to do
is you have to ship all of these
packages within 3 days. On a single day
you can have one boat that can carry all
your packages but that boat will have
some capacity. So you need to minimize
the weight required for the boat. So try
to think like this. If I have a boat
that has an infinite capacity just on
day one, I can load all of these
packages and send it away. Right? I was
able to ship all the packages in just
one day. But that is not the answer. I
need to find the minimum weight capacity
required for the boat. And I also have
to use up all of my 3 days. That is also
a very big hint. So what am I defining
over here? I am defining a kind of
search space. I know that I cannot have
a boat with a capacity zero because if
it is zero, I cannot ship any packages.
Can I have a capacity of one? Yes, I may
have a capacity of one, but I do not
know yet how many packages can I ship.
And what is the maximum capacity? We
just said that if a boat has infinite
capacity, you can ship all the packages.
But do you really need an infinite
capacity? No. If you have a capacity of
the total of all of these weights, that
is equal to 16. So if I have a capacity
of 16, then also I will ship all of my
packages in just one day. So what did I
just do over here? I made my search
space finite. I know that my answer will
lie somewhere between 1 to 16. That's
it. It is giving me a hint of binary
search. And how do I do it? I know that
my answer will be between 1 and 16. So
these are intentionally my two pointers.
Find the middle element. The middle
element will be eight. So what you can
do is you can try to keep the weight of
the boat as eight. And now try to ship
packages. when the boot was 8. On day
one, you can send 3 + 2 + 2 that is
seven. It is within the limit. I can
send the packages. On the next day, what
can I send? I can send four plus of one
that is five. That is good too. And on
day three, I can send the four remaining
package. So, in 3 days, I was able to
ship all of the packages. So, 8 does
look like a good candidate. But is it
the answer? I am not sure yet but
definitely we did one thing. Do you
remember how my search space was between
1 all the way up to 16? With binary
search what I did is I found out the
middle element that is eight. I knew
that with 16 I will be able to ship all
of my packages. I know that with 8 I
will be able to ship all of my packages.
It clearly means that any number between
8 to 16 I will be able to ship all of
the packages. So it is the time for
elimination. I know that the minimum
weight it will never be between this
range. So once again what did I get? I
am getting a left pointer as one and a
right pointer as 8. So once again what
will you do? You will try to find a
number between over here. Let us say you
found the number four. So what you're
going to do is you will try to determine
if you can ship all of the packages with
a weight of four. with a weight of four.
On the first day, you can only ship
three. On the second day, you can ship 2
+ 2. On the third day, you can only ship
four. So, you still have these packages
remaining. That means four does not work
for you. So, I can again eliminate all
of these options as well. So, what I'm
doing, I am applying binary search on my
answer space. Notice what I did over
here. My initial search space was
between 1 to infinite. I reduced that to
16.
Then again I reduce that to 8. I
eliminated this. Now I'm reducing it
between 4 to 8. So eventually you will
land at the perfect answer. And that is
the minimum weight capacity required for
your boat. And that is how you are
applying binary search on your answer.
Let us look at one more example. And now
I think you will be able to solve it on
your own. You might have seen another
similar problem. And that is Koko eating
bananas. Koko is a monkey and it has to
eat bananas from these piles. First pile
has 30 bananas, then 11, then 23, then
four, and then 20. Koko also has some
hours available. He has to eat all of
these bananas in these 9 hours available
to you. And now you have to tell me what
is the minimum eating speed that Koko
must have so he can finish all of these
bananas. The only catch with this
problem is that let us say Koko is
eating at a speed of eight bananas per
hour. So for the first pile he's going
to eat eight then eight and then eight.
He has eaten 24 bananas. So six are
still remaining. In the next hour he has
to eat six and then he has to stop. He
cannot eat two bananas from this pile.
That's it. This is the only catch you
have to be careful about. So how do you
find out the minimum eating speed of
Koko? You might have already guessed it.
It is very similar to the previous
problem, right? Try to think like this.
If Koko was eating at an infinite speed,
what will happen? In the first hour, he
eats first pile, then second pile, then
third, then fourth, and then fifth. So
in just 5 hours, he was able to eat all
the bananas. But he has 9 hours
available. So you need to use that. But
at the same time, if you notice, he does
not need an infinite eating speed. If he
is able to eat at the speed of the
maximum bananas in a pile, then also he
can achieve it. So if instead of eating
at infinite speed, Koko eats at 30
bananas per hour, then once again in
every hour he will eat all the piles and
he will be done. So up till now, what
have we done? We reduced our search
space from one all the way up to 30. You
definitely know the next steps, right? I
will have my left pointer at 1 and right
pointer at 30. So where is 15? I get 15
over here. So now what I will try is I
will try to eat at 15 bananas per hour.
The first pile is going to take me 2
hours. The second pile is going to take
me 1 hour. Third pile takes 2 hours.
Fourth pile takes 1 hour. And fifth pile
again takes up 2 hours. So how many
hours did it take? Eight. In 8 hours,
Koko was able to eat all of the bananas.
That means I'm still left with 1 hour.
But also, I know that for any value that
is greater than 15, I am not utilizing
all of the 9 hours available. So, what
I'm doing over here, I am reducing this
search space. I know that my answer will
lie somewhere between 1 and 15. Once
again, apply the binary search. Take the
right pointer at 15. And now, find a
midpoint. Using this midpoint, try to
eat all the piles and see how many Rs do
you take. Based upon this, you will find
your answer. And once again, binary
search helped you in your answer space
rather than the input set. These are all
the reasons which make binary search
super interesting. You are not only
applying it at your input space, but you
can also apply it at your answer space
as well. So whenever you are approaching
a problem, look for all of these pattern
recognition cues. They will help you to
understand if you can apply the binary
search technique or not. For example,
space properties. Your space is sorted,
monotonic, bounded. You have a
increasing or a decreasing function.
Sorting simply means try the binary
search. You are picking up an option
based upon a boolean condition. You are
able to discard some of the spaces. You
are want to finding out the minimum
value. you're trying to achieve a
certain target, some kind of a
feasibility. This is a very good
indication that you have to search in
your answer space rather than looking in
your input space. So try to look for all
of these cues and I truly believe this
pattern is going to do wonders for you.
Just tell me all in the comment section
below where else have you been able to
apply this binary search pattern. This
will become a very good collection of
all such problems and it will help you
also when you come back to this video
for a review and you will have all these
questions ready for you. Do let me know
in the comment section below and I will
be happy to discuss everything. As a
reminder, if you found this video
helpful, please do consider subscribing
to my channel and share this video with
your friends. This really keeps me
motivated and I can make more such
videos. Remember, you can now schedule a
one-to-one session with me and we can
solve any sort of doubts or questions
that you might have. Also, a huge shout
out to all other members who support my
channel. You guys really keep me going
because as a member, you do get prior to
reply to your comments and early access
to new videos as well. Stay tuned for my
upcoming video. Underland FIA.